throughout the last decade of my own
trading career I have tested thousands
of different Candlestick pattern trading
strategies and the one I'm going to show
you today is simply the one that still
performs the best even after all that
time so if you're struggling to find
accurate trading opportunities to give
you a statistic advantage and create
money-making trading opportunities for
you or simply put if you don't know
exactly when to enter a trade to give
yourself the best odds of winning that
trade and making money from it then
you're in the right place because in
this video that is exactly what I'm
going to show you how to do today you
will not only be learning the oddly
simple but effective Candlestick pattern
that I use every day in my own trading
but you'll also be learning the most
accurate price action trading strategy
that I use it in combination with so if
learning a rules-based strategy that's
already proven to make money over time
for me sounds good then go ahead and
click that like button for me go Ahad
And subscribe if you're new stick around
through the intro and disclaimer and
I'll be right back
[Music]
welcome back and let's go ahead and get
started first off Candlestick patterns
by themselves are not going to create a
profitable trading opportunity it's only
when you combine them with other price
action factors like Trend and Market
structure that they begin to become
remotely accurate or remotely give you
an advantage over the market and give
you a profitable trading opportunity so
the first thing I'm going to do is teach
you a concept I call the Market
structure reversal concept what this
concept is going to do is give us an
area of structure that is likely to push
price in a particular direction after we
have this area spotted out on the chart
we can then utilize the Candlestick
pattern you're going to be learning next
in order to enter trades in this Zone
and in order to create profitable
trading opportunities I explained this
concept in detail on our last video so
if you've already seen that feel free to
skip ahead but for everyone else let's
go ahead and get started I'm going to
explain it first up here on the
Whiteboard and then we'll take a look at
some examples on real charts to make
sure it's Crystal clear for you so when
we have a trending Market we're going to
start out with a downtrend when we have
a downtrend we have price pushing lower
creating a low then a lower high then a
lower low followed by a lower high and a
lower low this is what a downtrend looks
like now for this concept it is
extremely simple the only thing we're
looking to see happen is price push up
enough to break and close above the
previous lower high of a downtrend this
would signify a bullish Trend reversal
so we have price creating a high
followed by a low followed by a lower
high lower low lower high lower low when
price breaks and closes above the most
recent lower high we have a possible
Trend reversal and in this case
obviously it's in the bullish Direction
so this is the most simple version of
this concept again I'm going to show you
some examples on real charts as well but
the concept itself is extremely simple
so with this being the bullish version
let's now flip this upside down and I'll
give you an example of a bearish version
of this concept so since this is a
reversal into the bearish direction
we're going to start with an uptrend we
always have a high followed by a higher
low higher high higher low and higher
high this is what an uptrend looks like
now what are we waiting for to see and
to signify the start of a bearish trend
it would be the breaking close below the
previous higher low so in an uptrend we
have our low higher high higher low
higher high higher low when price breaks
and closes below the previous higher low
that signifies a trend reversal and in
this case that would be to the bearish
direction so this is what that would
look like and what we're doing is right
at this area that was the previous
higher low we are going to create a Zone
and if we see price pull back to this
Zone that's what we're going to be
looking for a very particular
Candlestick pattern you're going to be
learning next for entries and profitable
trading opportunities to hopefully push
price into a new downtrend and for a
bullish reversal it would be the
opposite we would be creating a zone at
the previous lower high right here and
we'd be waiting for a pullback into that
zone and that's where I want to try to
utilize the Candlestick pattern you're
about to learn in order to enter a trade
and give me the best odds of that being
a winning trade and this being the start
of a new uptrend so now let's take a
look at some examples of this on real
charts here we are on the 1H hour Alie
dollar chart and this is just price
action so what I mean by that is it
works on literally any time frame we're
just using this as an example so here on
the 1our chart what we have is a
downtrend that has started and the way
we point that out is we go from a swing
ey here down to a swing low up to a
swing high and down to a lower low this
is the start of a downtrend and for
those of you wondering well why did you
not use this as a swing low or use this
as a swing low well for me the rule that
I have for this is in order to count
something as a valid swing low I need at
least three green candles in a pullback
it can be more than three they don't
have to be consecutive but I need at
least three in this pullback for this to
be a valid swing low so since we don't
have that here this can't be my swing
low here we do have that but a swing low
is exactly what it sounds like it is the
lowest point before the pullback and and
break into new lows in this case we have
another lower low right here so
therefore this is not our swing low the
lowest point would be where it would be
this lowest Wick right here so this
would be our swing low which is why we
have our first initial impulsive move
going from this swing High all the way
down to this swing low hopefully that
makes sense after that we have more than
a three candle pullback pushing up to
our lower high compared to our previous
High right we then have a breaking close
below our previous lower low into an
even lower low which creates an actual
downtrend and if you have any trouble
whatsoever understanding that I have a
40-minute presentation in the last video
that we did that goes over this in a
very detailed manner I'll put the
thumbnail for that video somewhere on
the screen so you can see what it looks
like feel free to go check that video
out if you're having trouble identifying
swing highs and swing lows correctly but
in this case we had the start of a
downtrend so what we're going to be
looking for is the break of a previous
swing eye to give us an indication that
we could see a possible reversal out of
price after the break of our previous
lower high in this downtrend now a very
important concept to understand is that
anything between our newly created lower
high and our newly created swing low
that we only know is a swing low after
we have what at least three candles in a
pullback so now that we have at least
three candles in a pullback we can
verify that this is our new swing low
now that we have that in place
everything between the previous lower
high and this newly created swing low is
just a part of a pullback in the midst
of a downtrend until we either create a
lower low or a higher high than our
previous lower high so let's push price
forward and see what it does and as you
can see here price pushed around between
our lower low and lower high creating
this period of consolidation we have
right here before finally breaking into
train continuation so now that we've
broken into Trend continuation and we
have this three candle pullback what can
we do we can now identify our new swing
lows and highs because after that three
candle pullback we have a valid swing
low right here and our new swing high is
going to be the highest point this
pullback made before breaking into new
swing lows so with that being the case
our new swing high is all the way up
here with that new swing low being at
the bottom right here so in this case
everything between these two blue lines
is just a part of a pullback in the
midst of a downtrend and if we push
price forward you can see that we get a
new lower low right here without a close
below so that would mean this is our
actual new swing low followed by a
pullback of way more than three candles
pushing up here to our new lower high
followed by a breaking close below that
previous lower low so this we can now
say is our new swing high and once we
start to get a pullback from however low
this goes then we can count that as our
new swing low so right here we have that
pullback of more than three candles and
with that being the case we can identify
this as our new swing look now for this
specific strategy remember what we're
waiting to see is price push up break
above the previous lower high pull back
to that zone and give us an entry reason
that we're going to talk about in just a
second let's let's see what price does
after pushing price forward what has
happened now now our previous lower high
has in fact been closed above by these
candles here so with that being the case
what do we have we have a possible Trend
reversal situation so when we get this
situation what I like to do is create a
Zone in this previous area of our
previous lower high and I'm waiting for
price to pull into this area and give me
that entry candle that we're going to
talk about right now so we've pulled
back into our Zone I want you to look at
this next candle that
prints this is the candle I want you to
pay attention to and the reason is
because it's the entry candle that I
found to be one of the most accurate
Candlestick patterns to utilize for this
specific strategy and for most of the
strategies that I trade and what I call
this is a swing low engulfing candle a
lot of you are probably familiar with a
regular engulfing candle it's one of the
first Candlestick patterns that I
learned this one is just a variation of
that and the variation being it must be
the swing low of the current pullback so
in every case with this strategy we're
going to look to enter the market at the
bottom of a pullback what's the reason
for that well that is due to the fact
that we're waiting for price to break
above a level and then pull back to that
level so we're always looking for a
pullback so what this means is that for
our engulfing candle in order for it to
be classified as a swing low engulfing
candle it must be the swing low or or
the lowest point of this pullback coming
into our zone so this is a very simple
Candlestick pattern all it means is that
we have a regular engulfing pattern
which means our green body of this
candle is larger than the body of the
previous candle and the previous candle
needs to be red when we have this color
change situation from green to red and
we have a larger green body then we do
the red body that was the previous
candle we have an engulfing candle and
for this specific variation the only
difference is again we need our
engulfing candle to be the lowest point
of the pullback that has been started
coming into our Zone this is what I
classify as my actual entry reason for
this strategy so with that being the
case let's go ahead and set up this
trade this would be the entry and the
close of this candle is when I would
open up a position now after our entry
we need to identify places we're going
to put our stop loss to know when we're
wrong about the trade and when we're
going to get out being wrong and a place
to put our Target where we know that
we're write about the trade we want to
exit with some profit so for me what I
do in this situation is I utilize
something called an ATR indicator or
average true range you can go up here to
the indicators tab on trading View and
most platforms and find this indicator
all it does is keep you in line with the
current volatility of the market so it
takes the average of the last 14 candles
and it prints that average as a number
in the top left corner of my screen up
here in little red numbers this candle
has a 15 pip ATR so what I'm gonna do is
go 15 Pips below the lowest point of
that engulfing candle so here we have
down to the low of that candle about 20
Pips I would add 15 to that that would
make my stop loss 35 Pips so that is the
entry and stop-loss criteria for this
exact strategy next up what about
targets for me this is what I do I use a
1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio initially
if I'm not around my computer I will
just set a limit order and take targets
off at a 1.4 to1 if I know I'm going to
be around the computer though I wait for
this 1.4 to be hit I move my stop loss
to break even and then I look left and I
utilize the next level of structure that
will be hit above that 1.4 to1 reward
risk ratio as my final Target so that in
this case would be right here this one
is too close to my 1.4 to1 it's
literally almost right at that 1.4 to1
so instead of that level I'd be
utilizing this level up here as like a
final Target and I'd be managing
position up to that level which would
give me a little over a 2:1 reward to
risk ratio on this specific trade before
we take a look at how this trade
actually played out let's talk about the
story behind this Candlestick and why it
actually works so well this Candlestick
is showing that sellers were trying to
push price lower in this pullback from
the previous swing high and not only did
buyers not allow that to happen as
sellers started to try to push lower
buyers stepped in so much so that they
completely engulfed all of the sellers
from the previous candle so with this
being the swing low of the pullback what
that means is this was the sell's kind
of last attempt to push price lower in
this pullback and to push price back
into a downtrend but instead of letting
that happen buyers took back control
completely on this specific Candlestick
with this being a swing low engulfing
pattern so with this much buying
pressure coming into the market it can
be a great reason for entry when and
only when combined with other price
action factors like I said earlier with
Trend and Market structure as we're
utilizing it right here so with all that
coming together we have this trade and
this trade ended up playing out to be a
winning one as you can see here here we
are on the pound doll 4H hour chart and
in this chart we're going to look at a
bearish version of this reversal concept
and of a complete reversal trade
utilizing this strategy first though
take a look at a clip from our previous
video where I talked about exactly what
I was looking for here on the pound
dollar and I'll be right back to share
this bearish version of this strategy
with you next up let's take a look at
the pound dollar and first things first
let's go ahead and draw out our Trend we
have swing low up to swing High down to
swing low up to swing High down to swing
low up to swing high and what have we
just done we have just created a
possible reversal scenario the gold
trading strategy it obviously hasn't
happened yet but it's very important to
prepare for these things you don't want
to come onto charts and just start
guessing at where you're supposed to be
trading you want to go ahead and be
prepared for when these things happen so
that's what we're doing right now in
this case since we have just had price
come down and close below that previous
swing low we have a possible reversal in
Trend happening right now so because of
that what we're going to be waiting for
is price to pull back up to this Zone
this Zone has not been tested multiple
times looking left but that's not a rule
I have for this specific strategy for
the gold strategy I don't need multiple
times tested it obviously adds accuracy
but even without that I'm still going to
be looking for price to come up here get
between 1.29 59 and 1.29 37 and I'll be
looking for possible entries inside of
this area for the start of a new
downtrend here on the pound dollar so as
you saw from that clip this is what we
were looking at in that last video we
have price starting an uptrend by
creating a new high higher low higher
high higher low and higher high what
happens after that well if you remember
from our previous example what we're
actually looking to see is this previous
higher low get broken and closed below
just as we have right here so with this
being the case what I do in this exact
scenario is create a zone out of this
previous higher low level I'll wait for
price to pull back into this level and
as you just learned the entry reason is
going to be in this case a swing High
engulfing candle I'll show you an
example of that right now so here we
have that pullback that comes up into
our Zone and what do we have right here
this candle right here is the highest
point of this pullback so far from our
new swing low up to this highest point
that makes this the swing High candle
now on top of that I need this to be an
engulfing candle as well for a bearish
engulfing candle that just means we have
a red body that is larger than the
previous green body candle as long as we
have that we have an engulfing candle
and again as long as that engulfing
candle is in fact the swing high of this
pullback then we have what I call a
swing High engulfing candle and this is
my bearish entry reason for the trading
strategy you've learned throughout this
video and this is the exact setup you
saw me talking about in the clip from
our previous video so the way this trade
setup would look is an entry right at
the close of that candle we would use
that same ATR value above the high this
time of this candle so the ATR value of
the candle is 22 Pips I'm going to go up
to the high of that candle which is 25
Pips plus 22 Pips would be 47 Pips so
now we have our entry and stop loss set
for a Target initially again I'm looking
for around a 1.4 to one and if I'm not
around my computer that's where my limit
order is and that's where I get out of
the trade if I am around my computer
waiting for that to get hit moving my
stop loss to break even managing the
position down to the next level of
support which would be right down here
so in this case that would bring us to
around a 2.8 to1 reward to risk ratio
here on this specific trade setup and if
we click play you'll see that this trade
did in fact end up hitting those targets
now of course those were trades that
were in hindsight and it's because that
is just the easiest way to teach
Concepts and strategies but let me give
you something that's not in hindsight
this is something that has not happened
yet and something I'm looking into for
the remainder of this week going into
next week on the pound dollar here on
the pound dollar we have a downtrend
that has been created starting up here
going down to a swing low lower high
lower low lower high lower low lower
high lower low all the way over here and
what have we just done if we Mark out
our previous swing high and low which
would be here and here we have just
created a reversal situation again this
time to the upside by breaking and
closing above our previous lower high so
with that being the case what I'm
looking at on the pound dollar is for a
pullback into this previous level right
here and if we do get a pullback into
this level that's where I'll be looking
for that swing low engulfing candle for
a possible entry this level is going to
be somewhere between 1. 12833 and 1.
12809 I'll probably drop that all the
way down to the 1.28 even handle number
so there's a trade you can keep an eye
on that again is not in hindsight and
that has not played out yet if you
enjoyed today's video then you would
likely enjoy being a part of the TTC
Forex University in the University we
have an entire course taking you from
the complete basics of Forex all the way
through trading psychology risk
management multiple trading strategies
that I utilize in my own trading right
now and it is also a mentorship program
meaning any questions that you have
it'll be me personally answering those
questions for you on top of that the
university comes with what I call email
analysis those are trades I'm actually
taking throughout the week based on the
things you're learning inside of the
University so if you're interested in
that go ahead and click the top link in
the description to learn more or go to
www.th trading channel.com if not that's
completely fine too if you enjoyed
today's video make sure you click that
like button for me comment below if you
made it to the end and I'll try to like
every comment that says they made it to
the end and one more time if you had any
trouble understanding the reversal
concept we talked about in this video I
have a 40 minute lesson explaining
exactly how to do that so feel free to
go watch the video that you see on the
screen it's the last video we did you
should be able to find it pretty easily
if you just go to our Channel and look
at the last video right before this one
I wish you the best of luck on all your
future trades trade green and I'll see
you in the next video talk soon